Finding Aid of the UW-Milwaukee Dept. of Sociology Records, 1956-2005
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
UW-Milwaukee Dept. of Sociology Records, 1956-2005
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. Dept. of Sociology. Office of the Chairman
UWM Archival Collection 90
3.0 cubic ft. (8 boxes)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Contains correspondence of the chair of the Dept. of Sociology and its predecessor, the Dept. of Sociology and Anthropology, documenting staff and budget issues, curriculum development, the masters program, student affairs, and the physical environment of the department. The collection includes a complete run of departmental meeting minutes from 1981-2000, a complete run of executive committee meeting minutes from 1980-2000, and reports relating to 5-year reviews of the MA program in Sociology from 1980-2004. Three final reports of grant papers written by sociology faculty members are also found within the collection. The collection also contains syllabi from various sociology classes taught between 1989 and 2005.
In 1956, when the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee was formed, the College of Letters & Science created the Dept. of Sociology and Anthropology. In 1960, sociology and anthropology separated into two distinct departments.
Dept. of Sociology and Anthropology Chair
1956-1960 Gordon D. Shipman
Dept. of Sociology Chairs
1960-1962 Irwin D. Rinder
1962-1964 Robert B. Notestein
1964-1967 Hugo O. Engelmann
1967-1970 Robert Stuckert
1970-1972 Nason E. Hall
1972-1975 Donald Noel
1975-1977 Joan Moore
1977-1978 Jose Hernandez
1978-1981 James O. Smith
1981-1983 William W. Maryl
1983-1985 Ronald Edari
1985-1987 William W. Maryl
1987-1990 Gregory Squires
1990-1992 Eleanor M. Miller
1992-1994 William Velez
1994-1995 Eleanor Miller
1995-1999 Donald E. Green
1999-2002 Stacey J. Oliker
2002-2006 William W. Mayrl
2006-2009 Nancy A. Mathiowetz
2009-2012 Kent Redding
2012- Donald Green
Records of the Department of Sociology, including correspondence, reports, committee minutes, program review files, syllabi, and other files. Much of the collection is comprised of correspondence to and from the department chairs and chairs of the various programs within the department, mostly documenting curricular and policy decisions. Also of interest are program planning documents and files documenting 5-year reviews of the Masters Program in Sociology, which provide snapshots of the state of the program and advice from the report authors and external advisors as to the future direction of the program. A folder on sabbatical proposals provides an overview of Sociology faculty research interests between 1991-2001. There are final reports of grant papers written by Sociology faculty included in the collection: "Film Making in the Social Sciences," "The Origins of the South Atlantic (Slave Plantation) System in the Portuguese Atlantic in the 15th Century," and "The Study of Religion in Publicly Supported Colleges and Universities."
The records also include minutes from committees in the department, including the Departmental Committee, which deals mostly with curricular and policy issues, and the Executive Committee, which deals with questions of hiring, promotion, tenure, discipline, and other sensitive matters. The minutes of these two committees span 1956 to 2000, although coverage from 1956 to 1980 is spotty. Finally, the collection contains a large number of syllabi files from 1989 to 2005.
This collection was received in, and is organized in, multiple parts. Additional materials have not been physically or intellectually arranged and interfiled, and researchers may need to consult more than one part of the collection to locate similar materials.
The files are organized alphabetically by folder heading, then chronologically. The syllabi files are organized by course number.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
UW-Milwaukee College of Letters & Science Records UWM Archival Collection 1
UW-Milwaukee Dept. of Anthropology Records UWM Archival Collection 34
UW-Milwaukee Roberto Hernandez Center Records UWM Archival Collection 116
Administrative/Restriction Information
Box 7 is restricted in accordance with UWM Personnel File Policy S-42, as well as the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 (FERPA). Access to the personnel-related materials is regulated by Section III.A.2 and III.A.3
There are no access restrictions on all other materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
An unknown individual transferred the collection to the Archives prior to 1989. The department transferred accession 2007-050 in March 2008. The Department of Sociology donated additional materials in December 2011 (accession 2011-024).
William Velez, a longtime faculty member in the Sociology department, also served as the director of the Roberto Hernandez Center; files from his tenure in this role were transferred as part of accession 2011-024 and were added to the Roberto Hernandez Center collection (UWM AC 116).
Contents List
- Records, 1956-2005, UWM Archival Collection 90; 3 cubic ft. (8 boxes)
  - Alpha Kappa Delta, 1989-1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Introductory Sociology Courses, Minutes, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Department Committee, Meeting Minutes, 1981-2000 (Box 3, Folder 2-5)
  - Department Meetings, 1956-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Department Profiles, 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee
    - 1956-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1980-2000 (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
      Restricted
  - Film Making in the Social Sciences, Final Report, May 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Graduate Credit, Correspondence and Brochures, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Graduate Program
    - 1999-2004 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - MA Program Changes, 1996-2000 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - MA Review
      - 1980-1988 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
      - 1984-1988 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Alumni Questionnaires, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Joint Conference Committee, Correspondence, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - MA Program
    - Chair's Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Grad School Program Correspondence, 1994-1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Origins of the South Atlantic (Slave Plantation) System in the Portuguese Atlantic in the 15th Century, Final Report, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Program Planning Documents, 1986-2004 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Sabbatical Proposals, 1991-2001 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - The Study of Religion in Publicly Supported Colleges and Universities,1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Syllabi
    - 1989-2000
      - Course Numbers 101-248 (Box 4, Folder 1-13)
      - Course Numbers 250-380 (Box 5, Folder 1-22)
      - Course Numbers 440-928 (Box 6, Folder 1-19)
    - 1998-2005
      - Course Numbers 101-989 (Box 8, Folder 3-64)